SINA BAHARLOUEI

+6 years experience in research and development of stochastic optimization algorithms for large-scale machine learning models in academia and industry with a solid background in statistics, optimization, and data processing under uncertainty and adversarial settings.

@ baharlou@usc.edu

J 424-537-9656

sinabaharlouei.github.io/website/

github.com/sinaBaharlouei

WORK EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Research Intern

Bosch Center of AI

May 2021 - Oct 2021

Pittsburgh - PA

- Design and Implementation of Robust Verifiable Neural Networks Against Adversarial Attacks
- Published as a research paper at AISTATS 2023

Researcher Assistant

University of Southern California

Aug 2017 - Dec 2023

Los Angeles - California

Algorithmic Fairness: Designing scalable in-processing methods to promote fairness in supervised learning tasks

- ♦ Lowy, Baharlouei, et al., "A Stochastic Optimization Framework for Fair Risk Minimization." TMLR 2022. [paper] [code]
- ♦ Baharlouei, et al., "Rényi Fair Inference." *ICLR* 2020. [paper] [code]
- ♦ **Contributed Talk:** "FERMI: Fair Empirical Risk Minimization via Exponential Rényi Mutual Information." **ICML** SRML workshop, 2021.

Robust Machine Learning: Learning robust models against adversarial attacks (up to 7% improvement in verified robust accuracy) and robust imputation (0.14 improvement in RMSE for imputation of datasets containing 80% missing values).

- ♦ Baharlouei et al., "RIFLE: Robust Imputation and Inference from Low Order Marginals." TMLR, 2023. [paper] [code]
- Baharlouei et al., "Improving Adversarial Robustness via Joint Classification and Multiple Explicit Detection Classes." AISTATS, 2023. [paper] [code]
- ♦ Talk: "Fair and Robust Machine Learning Through Min-Max Optimization." Google Research, Sep 2022.

Learning in the Presence of Distribution Shifts:

- ♦ Baharlouei et al., "f-FERM: A Scalable Framework for Robust Fair Empirical Risk Minimization." NeurIPS OPT workshop 2023.
- Baharlouei, and Razaviyayn. "Dr. FERMI: A Stochastic Distributionally Robust Fair Empirical Risk Minimization Framework." NeurIPS AFT workshop 2023. [paper] [code]
- Dai, Baharlouei, et al., "Feature Selection in the Presence of Monotone Batch Effects." ICML SCIS workshop 2023. [paper] [code]

Selected Paper Reviews

Top ML Conferences & Journals

 ISIT 2019
 AISTATS 2021
 ICLR 2022
 ICML 2023

 UAI 2023
 NeurlPS 2023
 AAAI 2024
 JMLR

Server Side Software Engineer Quiz of Kings

May 2015 - Sep 2015

Tehran - Iran

♦ Implementing a ranking system for active players (>3M) via Redis

SKILLS

Programming: Python , C++, Java, Bash
ML: PyTorch , Numpy , Pandas, Scikit
Database: SQL , MongoDB, Redis
Optimization CVX , AMPL, SciPy
Big Data: Spark, OpenMPI , HPC

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Distributionally Robust Optimization

Scalable Optimization

Robust Deep Learning

Algorithmic Fairness

Fair Language Models

ACHIEVEMENTS

T

Top 3 Papers

ICML 2023 DP4ML Workshop



Bronze Medal

International Math Competition (IMC), Bali, Indonesia, 2011

:0:

Viterbi Graduate Student Fellowship



Editorial Board

International Journal of Data Science



Session Chair

"Robust and Fair Machine Learning in the Presence of Distribution Shifts." INFORMS 2023, Phoenix, Arizona.

EDUCATION

PhD (Operations Research, Machine Learning)
University of Southern California

Aug 2017 - Dec 2023

Thesis: Scalable Optimization for Fair & Robust AI

M.Sc. in Statistics [GPA: 3.97] University of Southern California

Aug 2020 - May 2023

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering Amirkabir University of Technology

□ Sep 2012 - Sep 2016

MENTORSHIP

 Mentor of Shivam Patel: Working on transferable large-scale fair models (Accepted Paper)